I'm going to follow over to the regular schedule meeting, I'm going to sit down, I'm going
to go over it.
February 6, 2021-3.
2, going to give us a couple of personal piercers.
I'm going to have three incentives that are going to be able to move out of 4 to 5.
I'm going to work.
I'm going to do a couple of Williams.
I'm going to start.
6.
I hope one of the live hospital program grant authorized to send me to her side.
You can't direct this.
Welcome and I'd hear me and I'm going to say, we got money.
What's the time to come in your asking for money?
I don't know if you guys remember last year we came in and we talked to you about the South High School.
We were chosen as one of the handful of libraries in the United States to be a pilot program for this program.
So it's so high school, it's something that targets people over 25 who've never got high school diploma or G&D.
This program we were given three seats.
We actually were able to fill five.
Since then we've had one person graduate.
We still have three doing the program and we actually had a couple dropout.
But getting one person through this program in a year has been a big success for us.
That's one person and our county that didn't have an opportunity to get a high school diploma at the normal age, I guess I should say.
So I'm going to let the camera talk to you a little bit about this program.
We were able to get a group for it and that's what we just drew.
Sure.
So the Excel High School program is again just what she talked about.
It's an opportunity for those that don't have a high school diploma.
It really limits those that want to apply for a job.
It really helps really limits those that want to increase in pay promotions as well as when you go to college.
So this is something that's really helpful for community.
So this grant was provided by upper home environment of libraries.
And we're partnering with upper home office and we're forced to implement to help fund applicants that can apply for this program.
So there's like two of your grant programs.
And what exciting is, they've decided to have an Iowa county, the 25 and older.
And they need to have completed at least a parade and then be willing to apply for a library card with us.
So the amount of other libraries.
And that's gone.
So we have a pipe for a report.
$48,000 for this grant.
So including 10 seats for scholarships and five laptops, five hot spots and accessories for
the laptop.
So there are many that just don't have those resources, can't afford a laptop or internet.
And so that's one of those that not everyone's going to need one.
So we only have five or five so they can kind of just change out as an individual's graduate.
And we also have five first-at support.
So we look five for 10 hours a week for the next two years for Cali and I, too, work on this
program to succeed.
So we're really excited that we're going to help us out with that piece.
Okay, and so just look at the three before, we have one graduate, three active enrollments
and two are wait lists.
And so we can't do anything with those that are wait lists and then tell if we receive approval
in city manager, Boe can sign off on the agreement as well as the claiming form.
So we can receive those funds and get started.
And we have a really strict application process.
So when it's a long time to go to our website, they do the initial five, once we see that
they need the initial requirements, we go ahead and push them through.
They have to do a three month visit test if they pass that and they will have an interview
with us.
And then if they pass that they will do a student pledge.
So we want to make sure that they really want to do this because the $100 will go a lot
of money.
And we want to make sure it goes to someone that really cares and will take the time to do
it.
And this group, this program also creates a full team to support the students.
So we're talking instructors and success coaches as well as advising staff to help them in a future
not just for the alumni.
And then that's all, that's pretty much it, it's a lucky question.
So when they first apply, it sends them a basic questionnaires, if you live in a lot of town
we are 25 and older, it does the basic outline.
And then once they've said that and we look at it, obviously, you don't know how many I've ever
ever ever made people, we don't even live in the state of the home, but they see free high school
and they think, oh, I'm not gonna apply.
But once that comes down, we get together, we have a questionnaires, we can send out to you guys
if you want to see what it looks like, it's basically how much time you have to commit to this.
Is there any head stress assistance you're going to need, so they're going to need to know
if they're going to need the internet assistance, a lot of top things like that.
And then basically, mainly, we want to set out and actually get to know these people because we don't
want them to just be somebody that's applied by night, they're going to sign up, we don't know if they're
actually going to commit to it.
So it's a lot of questions regarding that, I don't know, I don't have the exact list of them,
but basically, they're going to kind of give us a little bit of an outline on their lives
and how they're going to be able to finish with our written.
So what I thought, is that something they get to keep?
Just they will sign in agreement with us, I'm just going to work you on, stating that they're
going to be a part of it for us.
time they're in the program and then once they're done, they're lit on it.
I think they could finish on and if they don't, then they'll be responsible for this
thing.
That's something here we didn't know at the pilot and we already had hotspots, but we didn't
have to fully say to do that to help certain they might bounce up with this frame, I gave
us a little bit of a turn to that.
Which we had hotspots now, we have 15 of them and they fly off the shelves every week, we
have a full normal all the time.
So that was one thing, Caitlin was like, we really need to make sure we get things this
time because there's a lot of people who do a lot of that.
So when you say the hotspots, they'll let people in check them out.
We changed it from one week, which is where they check out for a week now, they can check out
for 14 days just in the evening.
We are hoping that we can apply for a grant or something to a grant for more to receive more hotspots
because our community seems to really, that's one of the favorite of the library every day.
So this actually is bumping down into classes like you would take at high school.
So they're getting two or three at a time, they go on there and it's got assignments, it's
got tests, and then they do a final exam.
One thing that's nice about it, so high school is actually at two hours available.
So if somebody gets stuck on something, they can just reach out to them and they can get help
working through their assignments, so it's more like an actual school, rather than do it
on your home all the time.
Yeah, this is a big program for a science school, which is specifically for a couple of libraries
to be able to offer a segment of technical information.
And people can buy it on their own, but it's $11 dollars, it's a really expensive, so there's not
many people who don't have high school of thumb up, but out of job, where they can make
it for that time, and then you get that better job, where they'll better promotion.
I'd like to close the two three sessions.
Second.
Perfect.
All right.
Thank you.
I would like to commend these two ladies from the get-for-stakes, ladies and gentlemen.
They are really struggling with four of them, but you know what, why she's this?
We have to be complaining, and really drive them crazy because they were laughing me up.
And we were a federal payment trying to find others.
We've talked to the tribes, we've talked to the civil lesion.
But these two are those two amazing buildings.
It's kind of something in the states that have an actual thing.
They were awarded these additional licenses.
As she had mentioned in the very beginning,
one of very few libraries that they might have did that.
So they should have been amazing job.
I'm going to congratulate you.
Thank you.
I'll follow you there as well.
I'm going to help me with these ladies here like that.
And they always come extremely prepared.
They always seem to be a lot prepared for people who were in the military.
Oh, libraries are good.
I don't know what I'm going to say.
Thank you.
It's coming up.
Seven.
We have to take on tax 18.47.
Excuse me.
This is the year 20.
We're going to bring them up.
We're not going to take our eight out.
We're going to take them up.
I'm going to issue you eight.
Yes.
We'll strip through.
Thank you.
You said that.
And then you go touch the slide.
That's it.
Down.
Put in.
There's a second.
Go to.
I didn't.
I don't.
A second.
That's a second.
That's a.
And a.
Five.
The second.
Nine.
the resolution that we should be seeing twice every year
will be required by the law to update our code
or minutes of those updates who are required to file
their file library, but the city court, and any court,
and so we just got this last supplement, number 16.
This is just a good, a good, a good official,
and allows us to file a file for all the places
that we want to be able to file.
Keep us in compliance with the law.
Correct, the question.
The question about doing this, we're limited to $50.
Our mind is the maximum we can do in cities that have not been
come in force to pay back 10s of thousands of dollars
to defend us in place that have not been done with this.
We should do a group.
That's a good question.
Is that, 7 or 7?
So, we'll find them in the right order.
That's a good question.
But then, it's just an awful hall.
Better to control the width, check the three code of orders.
So, as you all will recall, in 2016, letters
and say, let's one more group, the state question,
number 182, generally called, out the hall modernization in the hall.
We've taken a change to system and regulation about the whole of the State Department.
Cities were authorized to pass ordinances.
We passed our ordinance.
But since then, the legislature has consistently, every year,
made changes to the State law.
Without us making those same changes, every time they make the change,
then our ordinance in State law is in conflict.
And the State law is very specific.
There are a couple of things that we can vary within the parameters of the State law,
but the vast majority of the things we cannot.
This was most recently brought to our attention with the State having passed
what's called the Hot Dales to Go Act,
which allows for the delivery of alcoholic beverages to homes,
and this council had expressed some interest in getting that done.
And preparing for doing that,
I also found that they changed the age of rich employees
that can be used to worse than the grocery stores,
and had the license,
which changed it from 18 to 16.
They also, the reason to change is that it's just made in law.
They also changed law with regards to the health horses,
which is really pretty complex.
Which, of course, we don't have it all,
or since it's inside the city limits,
but the city is not enough.
But that doesn't mean we won't fit some point of time,
so questions are all going to be in that part of it.
To go on and on,
just to illustrate in 2017,
the legislature made 10 statutory changes to get out of the law.
In 18, they made 12 in 2019,
they made 26 changes.
And so, you know, it's reasonable to believe that
the legislature is going to continue to make changes to this law,
and we will always do change in our ordinance and act with it.
But another option would be,
and we can basically regrow our city ordinance
to say, our laws, whatever the signal is,
we would reserve the right,
and that doesn't make it be amended.
We would reserve the right to disregard
a change if we are legal.
to be able to, and that's a subject of much discussion,
what can a charter city disregard of state law.
And now, call and say, there's probably not much.
To do there is where we can set our own parameters
as the state law currently exists, is we can change
the hours of operation that a license,
off-premises consumption, the establishment is open.
We can't make it any more restrictive than what the state law is,
but we can make it more liberal than what the state law is.
Currently, the state law is that they can be open
from 6 a.m. to 2 a.m. the next day.
So, they could be open, pretty hours of debt.
So, if we wanted to deviate from that,
we could say they could be open for hours of debt.
Now, I'm not making that as a recommendation.
And just, sorry, sorry, that's an example of a place
where we could change what the state law says.
The other area that we are given some leeway
is in regards to the, what we call the occupational tax.
Right now, the city has its migration tax set at $50.
For whatever kind of license it is.
The state law allows us to, and this has been a subject
that's been discussed for a long time on my staff.
And every year, heading into budgets,
we talked about we need to change our occupational tax,
but that somehow just never quite made into the discussions.
So, we could change our occupational tax
and I'd submit it with the packets,
what some of the other cities have done with their occupational taxes.
So, for instance, rather, right now,
their occupational tax order, every different kind of license
that they have the packs on, is at $500.
So, that's the key times as much as what our occupational tax is.
By the end of this year, this fiscal year,
it goes up to $600.
But other cities, and we just, we ask cities what their taxes
are, which they're that, and these are the ones we've got in response to.
As you can see, some of them go home.
to $3,125 for a rectifier license and I really meant to look at what the heck is rectifier
or license was not.
We had a rectifier to put that somewhere in the city office and we could be a rate of charge
enough to $3,5 instead of aρχered dollar centred dollar centreture.
So, I mean, we can make these changes and keep chasing the state off, or we can just say,
we end up in the same law, and these areas where we have, say, some years later, we're going to want it to.
In this slide, for 30 years, just for discussion today, let's go ahead.
We want to bring this information to you today, and you can keep back.
I'd like to see.
So, I'm sorry.
How much can we make in the occupational tax now?
About $750 is our budget, I think?
About 750.
It used to be this high.
We used to have these old bees in the past.
And there's some interesting, some of our places that are supposed to be paid with $50 a year, don't pay up.
But for $50, it's just really...
You can cost a $100 a year, right, right.
Where do you already look where you go?
The sliders' doors, bars, the bees' doors, the bushings' doors.
There's a lot of them that we don't have in the community.
But, you know, what's going to happen in the future?
Where do you think they know the direct?
That was in the past.
I don't know what you're saying.
We used to have these bees that are similar to bees.
And then we changed it to $50.
Yeah.
We're getting our biggest interest in the dollars period.
We need to know what they have in the business.
Exactly.
Exactly, exactly.
That's where anybody in the south of all.
Right.
That they have to know the shows though.
Correct.
Well, it doesn't have ours.
This is what others did.
That's exactly what we're saying.
So what does this...
What can you use it for?
It goes to the general work.
Okay, so it's just doing this.
And then you talked about these laws changing rapidly.
Like, how do we keep our local businesses
of tries to what these laws are and how they change?
Like, if we just adopt us the state saying,
and then we have to re-responsible them to notify the local businesses.
No?
Well, that's the one that's the standard measure.
Yeah, the problem is that our supportance doesn't match
but instead of artists and they are planning a conflict
or what the state's telling us we have to do
or do we be all the way to the city's telling us.
So then there will be no responsibility on our part
and other words to notify our local people
that it isn't good practice for us to keep them a rise
and the changes that we can do that.
Well, we were doing it in part by sending us a single
person out of Bill or...
We do not.
Okay.
Now we'd like to know what is the ways we can notify this.
We were working with Dr. Mell with the published...
Dr. Mell.
We are working with Dr. Mell.
We're working with Dr. Mell.
We're working with Dr. Mell for the changes that I've done
in the next 40.
They would likely publish that information.
That's not a confidation.
I can pretty well assure you that the wholesale level
levels did that information.
That's not a confidation.
There's nobody that does that as to what our city changes are
although probably should.
But if you're matching that.
You're matching them.
There's no need for that to happen.
So the state has got the same contribution to that.
No, the state has a different name on the fees.
I don't think it's a tax.
It's a fee that they charge.
Our tax cannot exceed what the state fee is for each particular kind of license.
And if they change what that fee is, then that would automatically change.
If we were to adopt this procedure, there would have changed what our potential tax would be.
So there's being a presence in matching the fees.
Tax.
It's simple like.
It's not going to be a force.
If we were to raise enough to 500 dollars from 50, it was going to be a force.
Well, in that case, I'm sure that there would insist we get another
person's out to all of them.
So even now at 50 dollars, you're still on the bill, Sam.
I don't know.
We had.
I do know in the past we have contacted folks that didn't pay it.
I reminded them that it was there all this here.
Yes.
It's an annual fee.
Annual tax.
So I'm a little bit further here.
So if we're going to require these folks to play this.
We're going to be going to be a start and having the speech.
We're going to be.
That's a whole different thing.
And in part, that incident turns only election kind of nuts in it.
So, when I built it, it allowed cities to charge me.
I hadn't studied that one, like I did, just.
But, you know, another side of this is my selfish things,
and that I have to spend hours, hours, hours,
reading every change that the legislature has made.
And this is what I have to point for you,
because when they make a change, they don't just publish,
but it's a beautiful words that they change.
They publish the entire statute, which may be 100,
at one of 100, and then all.
And I have to go through the whole thing, and you have to put the election change.
So, I waste a whole lot of time trying to do that to this.
I'll show you how to improve it.
I think it's actually easier than that.
So, what I am saying right now, we are way under,
or we should be charged.
It could be charged.
But, the should is, you guys can't speak!
And I'll talk about that.
Okay, and we have here, as far as we can,
to be given that to you to a small business.
And then you make costores or others, in their chain,
give me their source, eat, put it in costores,
chain, break, get rid of this kind of chain.
Well, it looks like, making a must thing,
kind of goes on the side, this is a small worry,
I don't know, it's a regular thing, I don't know.
So we're not asking you to do that.
We need to make the decisions on what these were wanting
or any of that.
The question is, do you want me to grab this to match it?
Stay long, and then we can talk about what these you're wanting
to do to assess.
That's just something that's sad.
We've talked about the dearest, but the budget plan
rolls around are more delicious to assess than this.
That's instead of making changes every time,
I don't think we probably ought to go with this fight more deal,
but then let us do our own things.
I doubt that would make things easier on your officers if we just go home to stay.
Yes.
And a lot of these are administrative and mass laws that we're going to invest in for us
on a daily basis, but any time you be consistent between state and city, you're better
off.
And that would be a huge amount of system.
Yeah.
You know, I was giving you these numbers of legislative changes right now.
I think a whole lot of them have to be here with us, you know, in the dirt of this,
but I don't go that to my grip.
Well, I would say that five hours is a piece from his officers in the most state of
the system that we would do.
My grip would actually mean to go and stay at all much better.
How does that happen to you, really?
I don't know if the state changes, and I don't know if we're saying we'll get over the
long period of the state, you're still in a region.
Are you talking about the domestic?
We still need to know what the change is all, whether or not they affect what I do as a
prosecutor, or at least on this for those out on the street, what my answer is, yes, we need to
know what the change is that there's no grip, but we don't have to be regretting our ornaments.
A lot of times, when there's a deviation between state work and city work and state law, we have
to ask for a link, yes, we're going to go right, but there's a difference in how
it's going to apply to the situation.
We need to know if we can just say you're going to stay well.
I'll say, I would say go, not just up in state law.
I don't want to mention that.
Okay.
Do that.
I guess.
I guess bring it back, bring it back, bring it back, bring it back, bring it back, bring it back.
But that is that.
And we will work on it.
It's another thing that we need to discuss.
Let's go on in the city plan.
Just.
Okay.
Yeah.
But there's something.
You just kind of got all right.
Yes.
Yeah.
I mean, the big question will be, what do we want for it?
Can you explore for a retail liquor store?
What do you want for?
You want to go to a retail liquor store?
We can ensure that the companies do their job are important.
We will.
We go all the same thing as Mark and Mark.
We're in a run on that run.
It's been just a run, but there's not a run.
Given that we've always been to a hundred people on,
shouldn't we put that city on?
It's, or somebody's time wants to hear me, so I'm going.
Here.
I mean, there's a lot of things in our worktime
that the city folks go out.
So I'm sorry.
I mean, there's a lot of things that I can.
that we're probably not as important as this thing in court even that is still being done.
This is a common sector where, of course, we're actually, but we know, you know,
you know, the system of something in place or not getting an issue in this thing.
That would be the question that's had one group, what they basically use,
this is something we put in code, we have a module, we have purchased one,
you know, failing things like that.
It's been $1,000 to $1,000 to $1,000, but mainly, it's pretty expensive.
Yeah, I mean, all of it is just a question, but we can do that.
Absolutely.
And I would come out with, like, visual tax is doing their role before the end of the fiscal year,
or the next fiscal year.
So we have to have all of this by the end of the year.
So now's the time for us to get to the end of the year.
You know, we have to get the next step back.
You have to get one of the two.
You're a red, but I don't know if there is that.
Let me do that.
He said we want to be, we don't want to be a hard chip on any of our businesses.
All right.
That's what it's going to be.
You want to help me?
Yeah.
Okay.
You're going to let them proceed.
You're going to drop down from the council.
So that we're going to be doing a flood issue.
Yeah.
Under our public discussion, the rules that apply to special meetings too,
they would not allow for a kind of conversation that we had.
The last council meeting or what I think we're going to just say,
first council meeting.
So we're asking to modify those rules.
The same as they were from the last council meeting.
And there we have the discussions just like the last time.
There's a promotion to approve the changes.
Yes.
There is one question that the mayor may not.
all that. We were getting each individual, you know, in the open-to-net for public
decision, for questions, maybe each individual, if we get a time slot, the question
is, for the time to face, to answer their question room down against their things.
I don't know if they're really, makes a big difference when we're together. There's also no way
that they can be there. We're just controlling the meeting and waiting for the time on this.
I think this is a growth period. That's one of the decisions.
I don't think the answer is a big group of them that bring them up, because sometimes the answer
is longer than that. Oh, the challenge we're going to make sure they get their answer.
Do I have to challenge here? Is it longer trying to take something we're using our normal session
where somebody's coming up to make a statement? Not coming up to ask a question.
We give them a time limit of three minutes to make a statement. And then they're cut off.
Where is this? They're asking them a question. So I think, I think each person could get one question.
And then that goes back in line if they have a certain question. That's why it's, it would be set up.
That way, one person will ask them to give the question to our brothers and wife.
I'm bringing it up with people who don't get the answer to the question involved.
I think the answer is just, we'll make sure they give the answer a little bit.
That's all coming in.
All right. They might be agreed.
So.
So we're going to do that.
I have a question on that before.
I'm wondering.
I might go ahead and we'll be the same for the last time.
Excuse me.
Can I just get a question?
I'm going to go ahead and get a question.
Well, any other new business? What's the rhythm since they're posting this?
Did it?
Thank you.